I think he's very serious about wanting
to get the two sides to the negotiating
table in Istanbul. He has said
repeatedly that he's willing to make the
trip if it will make a peace deal more
likely to be approved or even to be
negotiated in the first place. And uh
the the Ukrainians say fine, that's
great. The Russians say it's not
necessary yet. There is no peace deal.
So let them work out some of these
details first. At the same time, I also
think that the president really believed
that he could use the bully pulpit to
push the two sides together and he's
been stiff armed by Vladimir Putin. He
doesn't appreciate being stiff armed.
So, I think
that allowing these Ukrainian um
offensive operations to to go forward is
one way in which the Trump
administration can try to nudge the
Russians to the negotiating table. You
remember, I mean, we were kids, you and
I, when this was happening, but I'm sure
you've studied it. Uh, when the US and
the North Vietnamese began to negotiate
peace in the Paris peace talks, peace
during the the Vietnam War, that's when
some of the fiercest fighting took
place. And it's because both sides
wanted to get a leg up that they could
then negotiate away in Paris. And I
wouldn't be surprised if if both the
Russians and the Ukrainians have come to
that conclusion here that maybe you step
up operations now and then you can
negotiate it away later in Istanbul. But
you know there's it's a complicated
because you mentioned that that
President Trump doesn't like to be stiff
armed by Vladimir Putin but he's kind of
being stiff armed by Zalinski as well as
a matter of fact. So this is the second
uh direct conversation between Russia
and Ukraine of course in Istanbul. Uh
here is uh the lead delegate for the
Ukraine side Umarov and coming out
talking about what they want to
accomplish. And as you do this kind of
sounds like that Umarov thinks he's on
the upper end of the power dynamic and
doesn't at all sound like they're
getting close to a peace settlement.
We've been telling Russia for a very
long time, this war must end. And the
whole world supports us in
that. We're calling for a real work to
end this war. The first necessary steps
are clear to everyone. A ceasefire,
humanitarian actions, and preparation
for a leaders
meeting. If Russia is serious about the
ending the war, it will move forward on
this. If not, international sanctions
must follow.
Okay. So, so obviously Russia is not
going to do a ceasefire first. They've
said that emphatically from day one.
Have never said anything different. So,
Umarov knows for sure that that's not
going to get done there. And then if
they don't, then we're going to going to
sanctions. So, is this an attempt, and
I've heard some people suggest that it
is, for the Ukraine side, not to stiff
arm Trump, but to try and coers Trump
into going back on trying to find a
settlement and to instead getting back
on their train with sanctions.
Oh, I think absolutely. Yes. You know,
we shouldn't underestimate Bod Malinski.
He's not an idiot. Uh sometimes we like
to portray him as one, but he really
isn't. And with the Brits, the French,
the Germans, the Poles, and a whole
bunch of other allies quietly pushing
Trump to keep up those Biden era uh
programs, aid programs, military aid
programs to Ukraine. I think that
Zalinski probably has concluded that
Trump can be manipulated at least in the
short term. If the fighting is still as
serious as it is with dozens of people
being killed every day on both sides, it
allows Zilinski to then go back to Trump
and say, "You see, I would love to have
peace, but the Russians are such ogres.
They're killing our people. They're
firing rockets at civilian areas.
They're hitting apartment buildings and
parks and hospitals. The Brits and
French and Germans are with us. We know
that you want to be with us, too. That
that argument might have a little bit of
weight right now. And and you know who
else says it wants to pile on to that?
Uh there's a whole group of people in
the US led by uh Sydney Blu Sydney
Blumenthal, Richard Blumenthal, and
Lindsey Graham. And that's right, Gary,
if you can pull this one up out of the
car here. Uh Jack Keane was also pretty
uh emphatic earlier today. So the
leverage has got to be I think number
one military assistance and give them
the robust air defense systems and the
other things they desperately need. Why
is that? Because once Putin sees that
the United States is still committed to
Ukraine, he knows he can't achieve
victory. The evidence is already right
in front of us. We're 39 months into the
war, Maria. 39 long months. That's how
much time it took for us to defeat Nazi
Germany. And Putin has not succeeded. He
hasn't even taken the entire Dombas
region, which is what he wanted to take
in 2014. So, he cannot succeed if the
United States is providing military
assistance. He knows that for a fact.
Second thing, let's issue the crippling
sanctions. That is all part of the
process. Yeah, there you go with those
crippling sanctions again. But John, I
got to ask you. We've had now nearly
three and a half years of crippling
sanctions, and it has had the opposite
effect. Russia's economy is stronger
than it was, not weaker. Ours is weaker
than it was, not stronger. And Russia
keeps going forward on the battlefield.
So, come on, man. What gives? Yeah,
Danny, I if there has ever been a lesson
for the United States on sanctions, it
has been this conflict. The the Russian
The Russians have not been harmed by
sanctions. Not in any way. There are
gigantic Russian markets available in
China, in India, all over the rest of
the world. And the Chinese have had I'm
sorry, the Russians have had no problem
at all selling their oil and their
natural gas and anything else they want
to sell. Most of the world does not have
sanctions on Russia. So, we can sanction
Russia from now until kingdom come. It's
not going to harm them in any way. Just
like in Iran, the Iranians lack for
nothing. nothing. They don't need us.
They don't need Wall Street. They don't
need American investment. They have
Russian and Chinese investment and
others. So, this ought to be a lesson to
the United States that sanctions don't
work. If anything, they harm only the
poorest and most vulnerable in the
target country. We need to do something
else. Oh, I have an idea. Like maybe
negotiations. We used to joke when I was
in the CIA. We used to joke about the
George W. Bush administration and how we
had never seen anybody work so hard to
not talk to our enemies. The situation
was the same under Joe Biden. It It's
hard to to think back on an
administration where they worked so hard
to not talk to our
enemies. So maybe if we talk to them and
let the diplomats do what they're being
paid to do, we might accomplish
something that sanctions have been
unable to accomplish. Now, let me ask
you a question here kind of related to
that in terms of uh especially back to
the decision maker in the United States
of of President Trump. One wonders how
much how much accurate information he's
been given by I mean, let's just say the
CIA since that's what you have some
experience with in in accurately
assessing what the balance of power
between the two sides is in all the
areas you're talking about logistics,
diplomatic, manpower, etc. everything
that goes into what makes a nation state
have the power to fight and win a war.
And obviously it's off the charts in the
favor of the Russian side. Uh but
sometimes I get the idea that that
Trump hears things like uh well let me
give you an example. So, uh, the UN
ambassador for Russia, Nenzia,
Ambassador Nenzia went on the UN
Security Council just a couple of days
ago and said that, "Hey, by the way,
we'd love to do diplomacy, but if not,
yeah, Gary, hang on. Sorry if you
complain.
As long as Kiev tries to prolong the war
and provoke Russia by striking
residential and civilian infrastructure
on our territory, we will continue our
special military operation and destroy
objects associated with the military
potential of the Kiev regime. and no new
anti-Russian sanctions, arm supplies to
Ukraine, or other hostile steps towards
Russia will prevent the inevitable
military defeat of the Zalinski
regime. The choice is now up to Ukraine.
Peace as a result of negotiations or
inevitable defeat on the battlefield
with different conditions for ending the
conflict. So, you could say if you're
Trump, just you say, "All right, I got
Zillinsky here talking that they're
going to win and they just need all this
support here and that they can turn the
tide, etc." And then I got the the
Russian side over here with Nenzia in
this case saying that no, we're either
going to take what we want on
negotiations with this 12-point plan
they put out, which is basically terms
of surrender, or we're going to win on
the battlefield. Now, Trump just looking
at the two of this and any any American
for that matter can go, well, they're
both just, you know, grandstanding, etc.
But if you look at the power dynamics
behind, one can back up the words and
one can't. So, if that was the case,
then you would not want to play an a
general. They're trying to balance
things out, but you would tell this
side, "Dude, you guys got to get off the
table here or get off your butt and get
to the table or I'm going to walk." I
mean, how do you see that part? Yeah, I
have to agree with you. One of the
things too that we're not talking about,
when I say we, I mean Americans and and
especially American policy makers, is
that the the Russians have a virtually
unlimited supply of ground troops that
they can just throw into the into the
meat grinder. um not just Russians and
there have been huge losses on the
Russian side and that's because of
Russian military strategy but North
Koreans and Bellarussians and some
reports indicating Chinese who have
volunteered to go to Russia or go to the
front lines and fight on behalf of
Russia. Ukraine is a much smaller
country. They can't keep this up
forever. The Russians can keep it up
forever and Russia is a nuclear power.
So I'm going to make a guess here or
make a prediction. It's not going to be
very bold or creative, but what we're
going to see in the end is that the
Russians keep uh the disputed
territories, the Donbass, Donets,
Gluhans, Keron, they're going to keep
Crimea. Uh Ukraine will never ever be a
member of NATO. Uh they they'll likely
join the European Union eventually,
maybe even on a fast track. But I think
that the that the Russians are going to
get 90% of what they want. The one thing
they might not get is probably the least
important, and that's what the Russians
are calling denazification of the
Ukrainian regime. Um, the Ukrainians
always argue that there are no Nazis.
There may be a handful of neo-Nazis, but
not in any positions of power. I think
the Russians repeat that for propaganda
purposes. I think they'll probably be
willing to negotiate it